a lot of my favorite personal trades
come from reversals this is where you're
looking to catch the start of a new
trend which means you can get in and
then ride a lot of profits out of one
single move in this video I'm going to
be showing you the entry models the
criteria and the methods you can use to
start successfully trading market
reversals so that you too can identify
the start and the end of Trends and
catch all the profit in the middle let's
get to it so the first thing we need to
cover is the context around reversals
versus continuations and where these
reversal trades are going to be taking
place there are a couple of phases the
Market's moving in here we have a
downtrend and then we have a shift into
an uptrend a downtrend is taking place
when the market is continually forming
lower lows and lower highs and the
breaks of structure are leading through
into new lows and uptrend obviously is
the other way round where these higher
highs and higher lows are continually
forming and each break of structure
breaks us into a new high so in a
reversal trade we we are not looking to
trade through the downtrend we are not
looking to trade through the uptrend
instead we are looking to trade that
small piece of price action in the
middle the kind of crossover point
between the uptrend and the downtrend
and our goal here is to buy into the
start of a new uptrend or in a bearish
scenario it's to sell into the start of
a new downtrend now what we're looking
for when it comes to trading reversals
is the area in price where the market
starts shifting from higher highs and
higher lows
into lower lows and lower highs so it's
this area here that confirms that change
in the trend Direction and it's actually
this area here that we're going to be
looking at building our entry criteria
to get into positions so we would be
looking to sell this level to then take
the market down into a new bearish trend
now of course as we've said we can also
do this the other way so if we see a
market shifting from lower lows and
lower highs where it's in a clear
downtrend breaking structure against
that Trend and trading into higher highs
and higher lows then we would be using
this area to actually take buys and the
idea here would be to buy into the start
of a new uptrend so these setups are
pretty high probability and they are
pretty high reward as well because we're
entering into the start of a new
trending movement whether it's the sell
side or the buy side we're basically
getting in early so we can hold this
trade for quite some time as opposed to
a continuation trade where we may be
looking to take profits once the market
starts to bottom out at each one of the
previous lows we are getting in early at
this point not late so we can actually
hold this for quite some time and tackle
some of those previous swing highs or in
a bearish scenario swing lows that the
market formed in its previous phase of
trending price action so that is an
explanation as to what reversals really
are we're looking at that crossover
point between uptrends and downtrends
and we are looking to get in early to
catch the momentum of a new trend let's
take a look at the entry model that
we're going to be using for our reversal
trade trading strategy it looks just
like this and it's actually very simple
in the case of a downtrending market
reversing into an uptrending Market this
is where we would be looking to buy I
want to explain this entry model to you
from the beginning so let's first
consider the buying versus selling
battle when there is more selling volume
coming into a market whether that means
there are more sellers or just more
units being sold than bought that drives
a market down because in order for
people to buy into a market we need to
see demand if there is no demand to buy
at this price here then sellers have to
lower the price for buyers and it will
continue to move like this until buyers
are happy to actually purchase units at
this price now of course some people
will be purchasing through these levels
but we need to see significant control
coming in from the buyers which means we
need to see all of the sellers selling
out of their positions and the buyers
actually happy enough to take positions
that the market starts to shift to the
upside so when the market moves from
lower lows and lower highs formulates
its low and then gets a big drive up
which breaks structure and creates a
higher high this is where the buyers
have taken control now when we see
buyers take control of a market like
this forcing a leg up in the market to
create a new high a break of structure
this is where we can happily start to
look for buys if the market is to pull
back to where we want to buy from that
area for buys is going to be just here
we're looking for after a new high is
formed a pullback in the Market to
return to a discounted price level to
buy from and then we will be looking to
get in with the new control from the
buyers so taking it back to that buying
and selling Theory we don't want to buy
during a downtrending market because we
know the sellers are in control but when
we get that shift this here indicates to
us that the buyers are now controlling
the market so buys are the smart way to
move so we would then buy upon pullbacks
into discounted price regions to get the
best possible execution and we can
continue moving the market to the upside
just like what you see here this allows
us to catch the start of new trends and
get super pinpoint entries for our
long-term positions now I'm going to
show you a few of the different concepts
I'm going to explain to you what this is
and what this is and then we'll go and
take a look at a few reversal examples
so let's get to it so in this section of
the video I want to introduce you to all
of the different concepts that we use
inside of reversal trades realistically
there are only really three that we need
to be aware of the first is Market
structure the second is supply and
demand and the third is market
efficiency so Market structure refers to
the direction of the trend as we've
already discussed if a market is making
lower lows and lower highs consistently
this is a downtrend and if a market is
making higher highs and higher lows
consistently this is an uptrend now as
we mentioned reversals are the area
where the market makes that first
initial shift and our idea is to buy
reversals to lead into new trending
directions so by taking a look at this
example the first thing we can see is
that we have a break of structure just
here so after forming lower lows and
lower highs we created this low here and
then the market went up and rallied to
create a higher high so this is the
first sign where we're seeing those
buyers take control okay closing up at
this high this indicates to us that the
downtrend for now is over and is ready
to start trading into an upward leg of
price action which allows us to look for
our opportunities to buy the second
thing we want to consider is market
efficiency also known as
imbalances so the market trades in two
phases
efficient ranges and inefficient ranges
an efficient range for the record is
something like this where we continually
move down and pull back in a very neat
manner every time we open a supply Zone
the market comes and retests that Supply
Zone there is no open price ranges left
open inside a piece of price action like
this okay every time we push down we
pull back up to fill the range before
pushing down again now an imbalanced
price range or an inefficient price
range is actually just an open Gap in
price so if we take a look at where I've
drawn this Arrow ignoring this piece of
price action for now once we had this
big drive up we opened what we would
call an imbalance from this candle
here from this candle here up at the top
all the way down to this candle here at
the bottom so here in this candle we
have an imbalance or an open price range
here we have imbalance or open price
range this candle is actually retested
Wick to Wick there but we have more more
imbalance here so this candle this
candle and this candle are imbalanced
we're going to be considering all of the
imbalance so we need to consider that
this is also an imbalanced price range
now when we see an imbalance what we are
generally expecting to see is before the
market continues moving in this
direction a fill of the imbalance so
we're not trading this like the newer
mentioned fvg that people are trading
nowadays this is an imbalance the
original version of the fvg concept we
don't look to trade out of imbalance
price ranges but we look to see them
filled now to show you what I mean here
if we pull this imbalance all the way
over the imbalance is everywhere Above
This Wick okay above the line that I've
just drawn on as you can see before the
market makes its larger movement to the
upside to create a new higher high at
this point all of the imbalance that we
created through this price range here
has been filled with this push down and
this reversal that we see in the low
down there so then the third and final
concept is supply and demand supply and
demand refers to zones that we Mark at
the low or high of significant movements
in the market this one down here is
going to be a demand Zone what it
indicates is an area of institutional
demand or institutional willingness to
buy the reason that this shows that is
because here we see we have this kind of
sideways candle or basically the
reversal point from down to up before a
significant drive to the upside this
tells us that this price range pretty
much between this low and this high was
seen as a good level to buy from for
institutional participants and we saw
significant amounts of buying take place
here which is why we had such a strong
move to the upside from there our Simple
Theory is now if this was seen as a good
level to buy from before it will likely
be seen as a good level to buy from if
it is retested again so we look to buy
from these demand areas understanding
that they are seen as very favorable or
discount prices for Market participants
to buy from and we just want to join
that flow and make sure we're getting in
around the same discount price levels so
to pair the three concepts together we
are first of all looking for a market
that is moving from lower lows and lower
highs shifting into higher highs then in
order to buy from a higher low we want
to find an imbalanced price range which
is going to be this area here with a
demand Zone beneath the imbalan price
range once the imbalance is filled we
then want to buy from the demand Zone
and this is always generally going to be
taking place using buy limits the reason
for that is we don't need to use any
confirmational entries because we
already have our confirmation entry so a
confirmation entry if you haven't
watched any of my other videos is a
piece of price action that looks like
this where we are looking for the market
to come into our demand Zone and then we
are looking for the same thing we've
pretty much just explained of the market
breaking from lower lows and lower highs
into higher highs and higher lows and we
will then look to buy here now the
reason we don't really need to use this
fractal confirmation is because we've
already got this confirmation forming
here so we don't actually need to do
this to get our entries we can just fire
straight into the trade with a buy limit
once that level has been met we have our
higher time frame confirmation all we
want to do with this imbalance and
demand format is use this to get into
our trades so our actual opportunity
would look something like this with a
Buy on the demand a stop loss beneath
the swing low and then a Target
extending either into the previously
formed swing High which would be this
level here or extending even further
here we have an imbalanced Supply Zone
that's a good way to Target here to
continue the larger Trend and that is a
hypothetical example of pretty much
exactly what a confirmation entry is
going to look like when you're trading
it and exactly what some of the entries
that I'm going to show you now look like
as well so we look for that reversal
from lows into highs find the imbalanced
demand Zone and then use a buy limit to
buy once the imbalanced demand Zone has
been retested nice and simple now in the
instance of a bearish market we would
look for the same but flipped upside
down we want to see a bullish Market
that is breaking into lower lows and
then in order to sell the lower high we
want to find imbalanced Supply so the
only thing that really differs in a
short scenario is we're not looking to
buy demand we're looking to sell Supply
Supply zone is exactly the same as a
demand Zone but preceding a large
selling move rather than a buying move
so this candle before the large impulse
down is exactly where we would want to
sell and then when this Supply zone is
met our sell limit at this level would
get us into a trade with a stop loss
over the swing high like so and a Target
down at any clear imbalanced price range
such as an open imbalance demand so that
is the format the concepts and the way
that we are going to be executing pretty
much the entry model laid out for you in
terms of buy setups and sell setups now
let's go and take a look at two more
examples of reversal trades so that you
can see what they look like in different
Market scenarios so here's an example of
a reversal trade taking place in the
market we're looking at Euro USD here we
can see over to the left we have an area
of demand over here okay now this is
important because this is the context
behind our trade you don't just want to
take any random reversal from anywhere
It generally is going to come from an
area of demand somewhere in a previous
Trend in the market so we can see that
there was a clear up trending Market but
this is since given way this demand Zone
here is the final inefficient demand
zone so you can see from this low
onwards we have an efficient price range
where every push away has been followed
by a pullback up until this demand here
where we had a drive away and an
imbalance left open now this has then
been filled after the market shifted
into a downtrend so we saw the market
moving up break into a downtrend retest
this area just here of demand and now
we're starting to see a reversal coming
back and way so this would be our
reversal execution then it's coming from
a demand Zone let's break down the
actual ual format of this entry so we
can see this would be where you'd be
taking continuation trades or prot Trend
trades throughout this falling Market
but when the market comes down to this
point just here and formulates a lower
high before the lower low we create a
break of structure through this high so
to Mark out the trend we basically come
down form our lower high lower low and
then have a break of structure to the
upside okay so our final bearish break
of structure takes place here and then
our first bullish break of structure
which actually reverses the market
Direction takes place here this is where
we start to break structure from bearish
to bullish if we then take a look down
at the extreme down at the low just here
we are now looking for as discussed a
pullback to then buy from we want to get
a discounted buy discount price level so
we don't just want to immediately buy
into the market right here where the
market has actually created this new
High cuz this is not a prime entry we're
going to want to see a pullback to get a
discounted buy to get the best possible
risk reward and best returns from this
trade so we would use our demand Zone
tool to find our imbalanced demand Zone
where's that going to be well there is
no imbalance demand here this is an
efficient range then there is imbalance
left open here leading us towards this
candle as a demand so my demand zones
are drawn as the last candle before the
impulse so the final candle that's kind
of moving side sideways or slowly before
the impulsive move Begins the impulsive
move being the strong imbalance candles
that create the change in the trend so
we're now simply looking for a pullback
towards this demand to buy from and as
we discussed because we've now seen the
confirmational shift we don't need to
wait for any additional confirmation
inside of this area this for example is
just simply unnecessary in a trade like
the one we're looking at so what we
would do is place a buy limit just here
on this demand as stop loss can
generally go first of all beneath the
swing low or potentially such as in an
example like this beneath the demand now
why could we trust putting this under
demand well that's because if the market
is able to come under this low there is
no reason with this wig that the market
should react inside that level so if we
get a push down like this we will not be
expecting the market to trade higher
this would actually be seen as a bearish
sign because the market has evidently
shown this demand is not strong and
there is no more demand here to drive
the market higher so we could actually
go with a nice refined stop- loss to get
maximum reward out of this trade now the
thing with reversal trades is we are
joining in at the start of a trend so we
can actually run these trades for a very
long time if we're anticipating that
this bearish trend is now going to be
reversed we could realistically look to
trade this all the way back up to the
structural highs so depending on what
kind of time scale you want to be
trading on because I know a lot of
people don't want to hold trades for
weeks or months
you can just simply Target previous
swing highs and actually because
reversal trades lead back into some
price action that's previously taken
place such as of course this downtrend
we get to see a lot of different Supply
zones and potential swing highs that we
could use as targets for this trade so
just to show a few here we could look at
this for Target one this Supply zone for
Target Two this Supply zone for Target
three you could even have this Supply up
here as a fourth Target and then of
course the swing high would be the final
fifth Target now I don't recommend you
partial take five times because by the
time you get up here you'll have such a
small amount of your position running
that it's simply not worth it but I'm
highlighting this possibility to show
you that whether you want to take trades
that you hold for a few days a few hours
or a few weeks you can actually be very
Dynamic with your targets you can go for
smaller targets to lock up profits
faster or you can really swing these
trades out and play them as a true
reversal holding them all the way
through previously trend markets okay so
now let's run this trade through we're
going to put it on 10x speed and just
see what happens you can see here we get
tapped into the trade the market pulls
down our initial execution would
actually be right as the zone is tapped
the market rejects inside of this Zone
as you can see so we have Wix
continually pushing us back up
indicating that buying pressure is
kicking in under these levels and then
we do start to see that significant
movement to the upside as you can see
the point that we just discussed about
using different areas for Targets this
initial movement would have driven you
through to Target one and Target two
pretty quickly then to target three and
four after a couple more days and then
if you were holding all the way out for
the maximum Target you probably would be
holding this trade for a good few weeks
in fact almost a month in this example
now even if you did hold this for a
month you've made 11% return think about
that if you can make between 3 to 5% per
month consist ently even 2% you can make
tens of thousands of dollars from your
trading you can actually make six
figures a year with as little as 2 to 3%
per month using funded Capital so if you
did this 11% trade on a $300,000 account
for example over the span of a month you
would have made
$33,000 in returns which obviously is
worth just holding through it's not like
you have to be running these trades in a
day or just a couple of days if they can
generate such large profits and that is
the beauty of reversals that
continuation trades simply don't have
when you're continuation trading such as
selling into the market here yes you can
run it down a little bit further but you
never know at what point this Market is
going to reverse the market trend is
already well underway and the likelihood
of this ending sooner is faster than if
you're getting in at the very start of a
trend such as right up there or for this
trade example so that is trade example
number one a very simplistic entry we've
done this on the 6-h hour time frame I'm
trying out some random time frames
really just to kind of switch things up
and show you that this is possible
across all time frames this doesn't have
to be done on the 6-hour time frame this
could be done on the 6 hour the 4 Hour
the 1 hour the 30 minute the 15 minute
the 10 minute the 5 minute or even the
daily time frame the concept here is
fractal structure supply and demand and
imbalance works the same on all time
frames so whether you want to be doing
this from a higher time frame
perspective to take very nice neat swing
trades like the one I've showed you or
you want to be doing this on a lower
time frame basis to intraday trade on
the 5 and 15 minutes you can do
whichever you want using these Concepts
so now let's go take a look at a low
time frame example of how to trade
reversals we're going to be looking at
the 5 minute time frame to show you that
this happens on the low time frames as
well so for our trade context we see an
area of demand here look previous to
that in these wigs we have absolutely no
imbalance left open through this price
range up towards this imbalance between
the demand here and this swing low so
this is a demand that we'd be interested
in seeing reactions from if of course we
retested it if we take a look at where
the market now is we have indeed
retested this level now this retest is
coming at the end of a downtrending
phase the downtrending phase pretty much
starts here and runs all the way down to
the point just here where we're creating
lower lows and lower highs in the market
okay now upon coming down to retest this
low here we've seen the market trade
into a new higher high so we've had a
break of structure just here which
indicates the market could indeed be
changing direction at this point because
we've seen that market reversal where
pretty much these lows here have broken
retested demand and then rallied to
break structure we could look for a buy
understanding that the market is likely
to now change direction to buy we want
to see a discounted price level so we
want to make sure that we're buying from
an imbalanced demand Zone and not just
immediately buying into the market
because our risk reward won't be so good
so considering what we've discussed
about imbalances so far do we have
imbalance here no do we have imbalance
here no how about here also no but then
this candle here we actually do have
imbalance above it right so there's an
open price range here there are no open
price ranges anywhere below that level
so our clear and balance demand zone is
going to be this last candle before the
impulse the last candle before we went
created that imbalance in the market now
because there is an efficient market
here once again if the market was able
to trade beneath this demand Zone there
would be no reason for us to be in a
trade so we don't need to clear the
swing low with our stop if the market
comes under this demand And Trades into
this efficient range it is highly
probable that it will actually just stop
us out and that the market won't reverse
how we want it to so if we were to place
our trade here we would go with a buy
limit we would have our stop beneath the
low understanding that if this demand
Zone fails to hold our trade is invalid
and we don't want to be in it anymore
and then for our Target we're just
looking for imbalanced Supply zones
above we have one just here which if we
take a look at the range beneath we have
an efficient Supply efficient Supply
efficient Supply so this is the next
considerable imbalance Supply Zone okay
that makes this a very simple and easy
target if we are reversing we are highly
likely to continue trading upwards
through the efficient range to at least
fill this in efficiency so that is what
our trade will look like in this example
as you can see it follows the exact same
format as we've looked at previously we
have our low lower high break into our
final low and then a push up into a
higher high now in this one we don't
pull all the way back for a retest
because there's no imbalanced demand
down here but we do pull back to the
closest and balanced demand to get the
most secure and highest probability
entry possible from this leg of price
action so this trade could return 4.2%
for every 1% risk rked if it worked out
and obviously if it does lose it's only
going to be a 1% loss which is nothing
that can't be managed
easily here you can see the trade played
out from start to finish after running
through all that context and letting the
trade do its thing we see that this
trade runs all the way through to the
Target pretty quick this is a trade that
was taken in London session and it took
2 hours and 20 minutes to play out so
that's a 4.2% return trade in 2 hours
and 20 minutes at $1,000 risk that is a
$4,200 trade if you were trading for
example a $300,000 account that would be
a $112,000 position secured in Just 2
hours okay and you can do that with
funded Capital without having to use
obviously massive amounts of your own
money so that is a reversal trade on the
5 minute and as you can see this works
on pretty much all time frames so
whether you want to day trade or swing
trade this approach will work for you
now one very important thing whether
it's reversal trading continuation
trading or any other approach to the
market is that you need to systemize
your technical process you need to turn
this information into a strategy that
you can repeatedly follow so that you
know you have an edge in the markets now
I have a course which is completely free
there's a link to it in the description
it's called seven steps to profitable
trades in there I'm going to show you
how to build your own first successful
trading strategy and how to build upon
that strategy to improve your returns
become a better Trader and make more
money overall so check that out if you
want to as I say it's 100% free and if
you don't want to do that there's a
video somewhere on the screen which I
know that you are going to love so
thanks for watching enjoy the free
course enjoy the next video whatever you
pick I'll see you in the next one